原视频名：Northrop Grumman has a nozzle problem
原作者名：BPS.space
视频来源：youtu.be/uS3sPPp5Iu0
原视频发布日期：20241008
字幕翻译：旋火
Sponsored by Brilliant.
本视频由Brilliant赞助
Northrop Grumman needs a little help with their solid rocket motor program.
诺斯罗普格鲁曼(后简称诺格)的固体火箭发动机项目需要一点帮助
And as an overconfident man with a YouTube channel
作为一个自信过头的YouTube博主
I think I'm the best person to help.
我觉得最好的帮手是我
It's a hard time to be a defense contractor with a $78 billion market cap
作为一家市值780亿美元的国防承包商 现在的日子可不好过
and an endless appetite for guzzling up smaller businesses
还有着吞噬小企业的无穷胃口
so what can we learn from Northrop Grumman Innovation systems'
那么我们能从诺格创新系统的这一观察结果学到什么
ability to innovate an exit cone free of a solid rocket motor while it continues to burn.
也就是创新出一个从固体火箭上分离出来的尾锥口 同时不影响固体火箭的燃烧
23 seconds into the second flight of Vulcan
火神第二次发射23秒后
one of the SRBs had a little hiccup and it ditched its nozzle extension.
其中一枚固体火箭发生了一点小问题 它的喷嘴延伸段分离了
This looked a lot like the extension failure in 2019 from the OmegA rocket booster test
这看起来很像2019年OmegA火箭助推器试验中出现的喷嘴故障
which Northrop semi accurately described as an observation.
而这被诺格模糊地称作一次观察结果
And at the very end when the engine was tailing off
在测试点火的最后阶段 发动机的尾部逐渐消失
we observed the AFT exit cone, maybe a portion of it
我们观察到后部的尾锥口 也许只是一部分尾锥口
doing something a little strange.
做了一些奇怪的事情
This is me when I do something a little strange.
这就是我在做一些奇怪的事情
All rocket nozzles come in three sections,
所有的火箭喷嘴都有三个部分
converging, throat and diverging.
收敛部 喉部 扩张部
This is a de Laval nozzle
这是一个拉瓦尔喷管
and when the gas is converging, it's forced to speed up.
当气体收敛时 就会被迫加速
You can think of this like putting your thumb over the end of a garden hose
你可以把它想象成把你的拇指放在花园水管的末端
which forces the liquid to flow out faster.
这将迫使液体加速流出
Once the gas reaches the throat of the nozzle
一旦气体到达喷嘴的喉部
it's forced to sonic speed where physics changes a little bit.
它就会被迫加速到超音速 此时物理学会发生一些变化
Once it's at supersonic speeds, any expansion is going to drop pressure further
一旦达到超音速 任何膨胀都会进一步降低压力
but continue increasing velocity.
但速度会持续增加
This expansion section is what gets lost on Vulcan's recent flight
在火神火箭最近的发射中 这个喷嘴扩展段就搞丢了
and if you can believe it, the flight seemed to work fine after.
如果你相信的话 之后的飞行似乎一切正常
The first two sections of a de Laval nozzle, the converging section and the throat
拉瓦尔喷管的前两个部分 即收敛部和喉部
are doing about 90% of the work of getting performance out of the rocket motor.
负责火箭发动机性能中的90%
Actually that's not true.
事实上并非如此
They're doing about 80% of the work.
这两部分负责的性能大概是80%
Let me show you.
让我给你看看
This is a program called openMotor.
这是一个名为openMotor的程序
It lets you simulate solid rocket grain geometry, thrust curves, pressures and lots of other things.
它能模拟固体火箭装药的几何形状 推力曲线 压力以及很多其他东西
In this tab I can set dimensions for the rocket nozzle.
在这个选项卡中 我可以设置火箭喷嘴的尺寸
Right here we have the rocket nozzle with the converging section, throat and diverging section.
在这里 我们可以看到火箭喷嘴的收敛部 喉部和扩张部
You're looking at the simulation for the Simplex V2 motor that I fired earlier this year.
你现在看到的是我今年早些时候发射的Simplex V2发动机的模拟结果
According to the simulation, the total impulse delivered is about 42,000 newton-seconds(Ns)
模拟结果显示 总冲量约为42000牛顿秒(后简称Ns)
but if I make some changes to the nozzle, we can effectively remove the exit cone.
但如果我对喷嘴做一些改动 就可以有效地去除尾锥口
This drops the total impulse to 34,500 Ns
这样 总冲量就降到了34500Ns
so the total impulse dropped by about 18%
因此总冲量下降了约18%
which means the converging and throat of the nozzle do about 82% of the work.
这意味着喷嘴的收敛部和喉部对性能的贡献大概是82%
This very small increase in efficiency from the nozzle extension
喷嘴加长所带来的效率上的微小提高
can also help explain why most solid rocket nozzles are conical exits and not parabolic.
这也能解释大多数固体火箭的喷嘴形状都是圆锥而不是(截面为)抛物线
Looking at them here in Onshape.
在Onshape中查看这些喷嘴
A conical nozzle for this solid motor has a straight exit cone.
这枚固体火箭发动机的(圆)锥面喷嘴 截面上的线段是笔直的
There's no taper on the diverging section
扩张部的锥度没有变化
but if we switch over to this liquid engine
但如果我们切换到这个液体发动机
for which I will provide no context and not explain what project it's for
(我不会说明这个发动机的任何背景信息 或者与之相关的项目)
you can see a very slight taper on the exit cone.
其尾锥口横截面就有轻微的弧度(锥度有变化)
And this is what I mean when I refer to it as a parabolic nozzle.
这就是我所说的抛物面喷嘴
It's generally a parabolic shape.
其截面形状基本上就是抛物线
A little bit of math tells us that
稍加计算就可以知道
a parabolic nozzle is always going to be a little more efficient than a conical nozzle
抛物面喷嘴的效率总是要比锥面喷嘴高一些
so why don't we see solid motors with parabolic nozzles.
那么为什么我们看不到抛物面喷嘴的固体发动机呢
The answer is that we do kind of see them but they're just pretty rare.
答案是 我们确实能看到抛物面喷嘴 但它们非常罕见
The GEM 63XL on the Vulcan uses a parabolic nozzle
火神火箭上的GEM 63XL使用了抛物面喷嘴
but most things in amateur rocketry
但大多数业余火箭
SRB喷嘴其实不是锥面喷嘴 只是长得像
https://space.stackexchange.com/questions/61416/for-shuttle-srb-solid-fuel-perforations-what-is-the-shape-of-the-double-truncat
or even in professional Aerospace like the Space Shuttle boosters use a conical nozzle.
甚至像航天飞机助推器这样的专业航天产品使用的都是锥面喷嘴
You know what. I'm not sure the SLS boosters have a conical nozzle.
我不确定SLS助推器是否使用了锥面喷嘴
I feel like I can see a slight curve on the exit cone
我觉得我可以看到尾锥口上有一个轻微的弧度
if anyone knows if the SLS boosters are conical or slightly parabolic let me know.
如果有人知道SLS助推器是锥面还是有点抛物面 请告诉我
The efficiency gain of a parabolic nozzle is not that significant.
抛物面喷嘴的效率提升并不显著
The nozzle extension at sea level is accounting for like 20% of the performance
在海平面上 喷嘴延伸段的性能约占总性能的20%
and a parabolic nozzle is going to add single digits of performance onto that
而抛物面喷嘴只会增加个位数的性能
so it's not that significant.
所以意义不大
The second is manufacturing especially at the amateur scale
其次是对制造过程 尤其是业余火箭的制造过程来说
it is a lot easier to cut a straight taper than it is to cut a parabolic curve
加工直锥面要比加工抛物面容易得多
especially if you're using a manual lathe with a DRO.
尤其是在使用带数字显示的手动车床时
It's just easier to go in a straight line.
走直线更容易
But the final and most important reason is the exhaust material itself.
但最后也是最重要的原因是尾气材料的性质
Solid propellant creates heavy biphasic exhaust.
固体推进剂会产生沉重的双相(态)尾气
By this I mean the exhaust isn't purely a gas
我是指 尾气不是纯粹的气体
like you'd see coming out of a methalox or hydrolox engine.
和液氧甲烷或者液氢液氧发动机的尾气不一样
There are some solid particles in there too, like the aluminum oxides
固发的尾气中还有一些固体颗粒 如氧化铝
and some of the unburned AP particles.
还有一些未燃烧的高氯酸铵颗粒
So in contrast to the relatively lightweight gas coming through a liquid rocket nozzle
因此 与液体火箭喷嘴排出的较轻的气体相比
solid rocket exhaust is heavier which will strip away ablative materials faster.
固体火箭排出的尾气更重 因此会更快地剥去烧蚀材料
Since most solid rocket motors use ablative nozzles, this is a big concern.
由于大多数固体火箭发动机都使用烧蚀喷嘴 因此这是一个很大的问题
So all these things considered I want to put some numbers to this.
综上所述 我想用一些数字来说明这一点
How did Vulcan make it to orbit despite Northrop Grumman doing some Innovation along the way.
尽管诺格在火箭发射过程中进行了一些创新 但最后又怎能入轨成功呢
Some quick math tells us why this is like not a huge problem.
通过简单的数学计算 我们就能知道这为什么不是个大问题
I'm going to use pounds because I understand them better
我将使用英镑 因为我更了解英镑
but I'll put metric on the screen too.
但我也会在屏幕上显示公制
Because sometimes people get unreasonably upset about that.
因为有时人们会无理取闹
Each BE-4 engine produces 550,000 lb of thrust.
每台BE-4发动机可产生226.796吨推力
Times 2, it's 1.1 million.
乘以2 就是498.951吨推力
Each SRB at liftoff is providing about 400,000 lb of thrust
起飞时 每枚固体火箭可提供约181.436吨的推力
and so all told the vehicle is producing just shy of 2 million lb of thrust
所以总的来说 火箭整体产生的推力接近861.825吨推力
so can you really lose one of these nozzles and be fine?
那么在失去一个喷嘴后依然可以安然无恙吗
Yeah, kind of.
差不多吧
If both boosters are doing 400,000 lb of thrust
如果两个助推器的推力都是181.436吨
and one booster decides it's time to innovate,
而其中一个助推器决定是时候创新了
my guess is that innovation drops the thrust down to about 330,000 lb of thrust.
我猜创新会把推力降到大约149.685吨
That's about a 17% cut on the thrust of one motor
一台发动机的推力大约减少了17%
but it's only a 4% cut across the total vehicle.
但整个火箭的推力只减少了4%
This also assumes constant liquid and solid thrust
这也是假设液体和固体推力(在飞行过程中)不变
which is not the case across this whole flight profile.
然而实际上并非如此
The GEM 63XL uses a cylinder finocyl geometry that is set up
GEM 63XL使用的是翼柱式装药
so the thrust curve is not at all flat.
因此推力曲线并不平坦
The other thing to note is that performance changes with temperature.
还需要注意的是 性能会随着温度变化
These motors burn a little differently when it is warm versus when it is cold.
这些发动机在温度较高和较低时的燃烧情况略有不同
Colder solid rocket motors burn more tame and more slowly.
温度较低时 固体火箭发动机的燃烧比较平缓 速度也比较慢
Hotter solid rocket motors burn faster and more angry.
温度较高时 其燃烧得更快 更猛烈
This is by no means a conclusive analysis.
这绝不是结论性的分析
But we can be pretty sure that the motors that are burning in October of 2024
但我们可以肯定的是 2024年10月固体发动机的燃烧
are going to be burning harder and faster than the motors that were burning in January of 2024 during Vulcan's first flight.
会比2024年1月火神火箭首飞时的燃烧得更猛更快
I did a bunch of math on the GNC side to see how bad this torque would have been.
我在制导 导航和控制系统方面做了很多计算 看看这种扭矩会有多大
We have about a 70,000 lb deficit on the right side of the vehicle
在火箭的右部大概有31.751吨推力的缺口
which is why you see this thing pitch so hard once the exit cone leaves.
这就是一旦尾锥口分离后 你会看到火箭倾斜得如此厉害
I'll spare you all of the math I went through
我就不给你们一一展示计算过程了
but the TLDR is that these GEM 63XL motors having a 3° cant on the nozzle absolutely saved the flight.
但总而言之 这些GEM 63XL的喷嘴安装角有3° 绝对挽救了这次飞行
Without those solid boosters firing through the center of mass
如果这些固体助推器的推力矢量没有过质心
the BE-4 5° gimbal range would not have been enough to counteract a 70,000 lb deficit in one solid motor.
BE-4的5°摆动范围不足以抵消一台固体发动机31.751吨推力的损失
Losing your nozzle extension is no good.
失去喷管延伸段可不是什么好事
The flight clearly worked but it's worth using this as an opportunity to talk about planned failure modes.
这次飞行显然是成功的 但值得借此机会谈谈计划中的失效模式
The best thing that can happen to your solid rocket motor is that it works.
对于固体火箭发动机来说 最好的情况就是它能正常工作
But the second best thing is that the nozzle falls out.
但第二好的情况就是喷嘴脱落
There is no better failure mode than to poop out the nozzle.
没有比把喷嘴脱落更好的失效模式了
Think about it this way you are now this solid rocket motor
这么想吧 你现在是这个固体火箭发动机
and you're feeling kind of goofy.
而你感觉有点轴
What do you want to do?
你要做什么呢
You could pop the forward closure but that's no good.
你可以弹开前封头 但那样不好
If you're attached to Vulcan you're going to damage one of the tanks.
如果你连着火神火箭 你会损坏其中一个储罐
and take the whole vehicle out with you.
整枚火箭都会和你一起整没
And if you're firing on the test range in the desert
如果(这发生)在沙漠中的火箭测试场
popping the forward closure means you push against your load cell
弹开前封头意味着会顶到推力传感器
and you fire the whole motor out like a bullet.
然后整枚火箭就会像子弹一样发射出去
That turns your static fire into a dynamic fire
静态点火也就变成动态点火了
which for reasons I shouldn't have to cover is not a great thing.
这不是一件好事 原因我就不多说了
If you're feeling goofy you could also pop the case.
很轴的发动机 也可以搞炸火箭壳体
This is a classic failure mode, a tale as old as time.
这是一个经典的故障模式 和岁月一样古老的故事
Someone drops the rocket motor and processing and your GPS satellite becomes confetti.
有人的火箭发动机和航电都掉落在地上 而GPS卫星变成了纸屑
19970117 Delta II 7925-9.5 GPS IIR-1 https://youtu.be/mTmb3Cqb2qw
We have had an anomaly.
我们已经遇到了异常情况
The only safe bet with solid rocket motors is to ditch the nozzle.
对于固体火箭发动机来说 保险的方法就是扔掉喷嘴
In all of Northrop's GEM motors which you can look at in the propulsion products catalog
你可以在推进器产品目录中看到 在诺格的所有GEM发动机中
which I love looking through
当然我很喜欢翻阅这个产品目录
the case and the forward closure are wound together as one part
外壳和前封头是缠绕在一起的一个部件
while the nozzle is always bolted on.
而喷嘴始终是用螺栓固定的
This makes the motor safer to transport
这使得发动机在运输时更安全
and bolt shear in a solid material like steel here
而在像钢这样的坚固材料上
is going to be a lot easier to FEA and calculate then shear out of a composite material.
对螺栓剪切力的有限元分析和计算要比复合材料容易得多
And composits are hard like even if you're smart they're hard.
即使你很聪明 也很难去把复合材料做好
In amateur rocketry this is just as true just not as important.
对于业余火箭来说 这一点同样适用 只是没有那么重要
We're not flying National Security missions.
我们不是在执行国家安全任务
We're just like having a good time in the desert.
我们只是在沙漠中享受美好时光
Typically a solid rocket motor is retained on both ends by radial bolts
通常情况下 固体火箭发动机的两端由径向螺栓固定
and if you want to ensure the nozzle comes out, you need fewer radial bolts near the nozzle.
如果你想确保喷嘴分离 就需要减少喷嘴附近的径向螺栓
Even if you're flying a high power rocket stabilized by fins
即使是用翼面稳定的大功率火箭
the nozzle is still the best thing that can fail.
喷嘴仍然是最容易发生故障的部件
If your nozzle falls out, the Rocket won't go as high
如果喷嘴脱落 火箭的飞行高度会降低
but everything forward of the motor is safe.
但发动机前的所有部件都是安全的
If you blow the case open, the fins are probably not staying on.
如果外壳被炸开 翼面很可能无法固定
Your rocket's going to turn sideways and likely shred
火箭会侧向飞行 很可能会碎裂
and if you blow the forward closure you'll do some impromptu stage separation
如果炸开前封头 就会造成非预期的级间分离
while also probably killing other parts of the rocket.
而火箭的其他部分也可能因此而损坏
This video is drenched in sarcasm so just to clearly state it.
这个视频充满了讽刺意味 所以我只想清楚地说明这一点
Congratulations to ULA on getting Vulcan into orbit for a second time.
祝贺ULA第二次将火神火箭送入轨道
It is genuinely impressive that it was able to suffer this type of anomaly and still make it.
它能在遭遇这种异常情况的情况下依然成功 确实令人印象深刻
I thought this would be a great opportunity to talk about failure modes with a little more detail about nozzles.
我认为这将是一个很好的机会来讨论故障模式 并对喷嘴进行更详细的介绍
And I got a real slammer coming up soon, too.
而且 很快我就会有一个真正的猛料
So make sure you're subscribed.
请确保你已订阅
We're going to look at X-rays inside of a solid rocket motor.
我们会通过X射线来观看固体火箭发动机的内部
But before we do that I want to thank the sponsor for today's video which is Brilliant.
但在此之前 我要感谢今天视频的赞助商 Brilliant
if you don't already have the pleasure of knowing what brilliant is allow me to help you
brilliant is an online Interactive Learning platform
built around the idea of learning by doing
I say this every time but I love working with brilliant
for folks like myself and probably you if you're interested in learning
brilliant is a great service and way to do that
learning by doing is the fastest and most effective way to gain a better understanding of something new
brilliant specifically focuses on teaching math data science AI programming and Fields of that nature
maybe you're looking to switch career paths
or maybe you're looking to up your game and add some new skills to the skill tree
it's easy to do that on your budget and schedule with brilliant
and they've even got a great mobile interface so you can learn on the go
from large language models to coding and python to data science
you can get started for free for the first 30 days by going to brilliant.org/BPSSpace
you can click the QR code or you can click the link in the description down below
I guess you don't click the QR code you more scan it with a camera
anyway this will get you 20% off an annual premium subscription to brilliant which is a solid deal
Thanks a bunch to Brilliant for sponsoring this video.
感谢Brilliant赞助本视频
Thank you to you for watching.
感谢你的收看
My name is Joe Barnard.
我叫Joe Barnard
May your skies be blue and your winds be low.
愿你云淡风轻
G'bye.
寨见